Let's just think about addiction,
because in biology
and in psychology, frankly,
it really often pays
to think about the extremes first
and then work our way
towards more typical circumstances.
Now with that said,
addiction unfortunately,
is very common nowadays.
I just heard a statistic, in fact,
that there is an 80% increase
in alcohol use disorder
among women in the last 30 years.
I talked a little bit about this
in the episode that I did
about alcohol and health.
Again, I want to be very clear.
I'm not somebody that is completely
against alcohol for adults,
provided they're not alcoholics.
Turns out two drinks a week,
probably fine health-wise.
Zero would be better if we're honest.
Zero is better than any alcohol.
But two drinks a week is probably fine.
Past two drinks,
you start running into problems.
Yet many, many people out there,
male and female alike
suffer from alcohol use disorder,
also called alcoholism.
The same is also true
for things like methamphetamine
or cocaine
or other types of substance addictions.
The same is also true
for a lot of behavioral
or what are sometimes
called process addictions.
Things like sex addiction
or video game addiction,
or any type of behavior that, frankly,
is leveraging the dopamine system,
but that engages
this progressive narrowing
of the things that bring someone pleasure
such that nothing else is really salient.
Nothing else is really pulling them in
in the way that their video games
or sex or pornography or alcohol.
Pick your substance
or behavior that you see out there,
or hopefully not,
that you might suffer
from an addiction to.
What's happening in addiction?
Well, addiction involves dopamine,
among other things,
often the opioid system, etc.
But if we were to think
about what's the stimulus in an addiction
and what's the peak in dopamine,
and then what happens after that peak,
it all becomes very clear
as to why addiction happens
and why it's so pernicious.
For instance, let's take cocaine.
Cocaine causes dramatic increases
in dopamine very, very fast.
If somebody craves cocaine,
what are they craving?
They're craving that dopamine peak.
They're craving
the increased level of alertness.
They're craving a number of things
associated with the feeling of being
under the influence of the drug.
But the stimulus for it simply
becomes that line of cocaine.
Or in the case of crack,
that crack rock
that they're going to smoke
and God forbid they're mainlining it,
they're shooting into a vein.
What happens is they snort,
smoke, or inject cocaine
and dopamine levels almost immediately
go up to a very high peak.
The time gap between the stimulus
and the dopamine is very, very short.
So short, in fact, that there's really
no other contingencies in between
that the mesocortical system
has to learn.
In fact, what does the system "learn"?
It learns cocaine equals
massive amounts of dopamine
equals feeling
euphoric and energetic, etc.
In doing that,
it reinforces the whole circuit
so that that short,
we can even say hyper-short contingency
is really what the system wants.
So much so
that longer contingencies of, say,
putting in the hard work
of generating a fitness program
or a professional program for yourself
or an education program
which takes not just many days
but many weeks and years,
well, none of that is going
to lead to peaks in dopamine
that are as high as the peak
in dopamine associated with cocaine.
That tells us something critical.
It is both the duration
between desire and effect.
When I say effect,
I mean the rewarding properties
of dopamine that are experienced.
That's important.
Very short gaps teach the system
to expect and want short gaps.
Makes it very hard
to pursue things that take longer.
When we say it's the short,
or in this case, hyper-short distance
or time
between the stimulus and the dopamine,
what we're really talking about,
if we were to plot this out
on a board or on a piece of paper,
is the steepness of the rise of that peak.
It's very, very steep.
The peak in dopamine
is coming up very fast after the desire.
In addition to that,
and this is very important,
the higher the peak in dopamine
and the faster the rise to that peak,
the further below baseline the dopamine
drops after the drug wears off.
In the case of cocaine,
it's a very fast
and very large rise in dopamine,
followed by a steep drop
and very deep trough
in dopamine below baseline.
You say, okay, so there's pleasure,
then there's lack of pleasure.
But it's worse than that
because it's not just lack of pleasure.
If you recall
what we talked about a little bit earlier,
that drop below baseline triggers
the desire and the pursuit for what?
For more.
This sets in motion a vicious loop
where people start
pursuing peaks in dopamine
that can come
very fast without much effort.
That's one of the ways
in which addiction start to take hold.
There's a simple way to think about this
and to remember if you want
to avoid this whole thing.
I mean, the first one is obvious,
don't do cocaine.
Don't try it. Don't use it.
Certainly don't get addicted to it.
Those are all one in the same, frankly.
I don't know many people
that despite opinions to the contrary
that use cocaine recreationally,
that don't at some point run into either
a financial, psychological,
physical, or some other problem.
The other thing that's absolutely
critical to keep in mind,
and this was discussed
in my colleague Dr. Anna Lembke's book,
Dopamine Nation and on this podcast.
Excellent book, by the way.
I highly recommend it
if you haven't read it already.
It's a fascinating exploration
into dopamine as it relates to addiction,
not just drug addiction,
but other types of addiction.
Again, the name of that book
is Dopamine Nation.
We'll provide a link to it
in the show notes captions.
The other thing that happens
after those big, fast increases
in dopamine caused by things like cocaine
is afterwards
when it quickly drops below baseline,
it takes a much longer time
to get back to the original baseline
than it did prior to using the drug.
Worse still, is that the peaks
in dopamine that are created
from more consumption of cocaine
leads to progressively lower peaks
and deeper troughs below baseline.
The whole system
is shifting away from pleasure
and more to pain
and the desire for pursuit of the drug.